<!--

    Copyright (C) 2014-2026 Philip Helger (www.helger.com)
    philip[at]helger[dot]com

    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

            http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->
<p>
  This page outlines how SMP and SML play together.
  The SML (Service Metadata Locator) is only central component in the Peppol eDelivery Network.
  The SMP (Service Metadata Publisher) is a decentralized registry for technical metadata. 
</p>
<p>
  Note: this information presented here shows the Peppol way which is different from
  the latest OASIS BDXL way. The SML currently used by Peppol (BDMSL operated by EC DG DIGIT) 
  supports both ways, but this page ignores the non-Peppol aspects. 
</p>

<div class="card">
  <div class="card-header">
    Table of contents
  </div>
  <div class="card-body">
    <ol>
      <li><a href="#prerequisites">Prerequisites</a></li>
      <li><a href="#create-smp">Create SMP at SML</a></li>
      <li><a href="#update-smp">Update SMP at SML</a></li>
      <li><a href="#delete-smp">Delete SMP from SML</a></li>
      <li><a href="#create-participant">Create participant in SMP and SML</a></li>
      <li><a href="#delete-participant">Delete participant from SMP and SML</a></li>
      <!-- 
      <li><a href="#migrate-participant">Migrate participant from one SMP to another SMP</a></li>
       -->
      <li><a href="#references">References</a></li>
    </ol>
  </div>
</div>

<a name="prerequisites"></a>
<h2>Prerequisites</h2>

<p>
  This page takes the following assumptions:
  <ul>
    <li>You have a running instance of an SMP server (that follows the Peppol SMP specification)</li>
    <li>The SMP server runs on a publicly accessible web server that has a DNS name assigned</li>
    <li>You have a Peppol SMP X.509 certificate that is compatible with the SML you want to interact with (production certificate for SML, test certificate for SMK)</li>
    <li>You have chosen a so called <em>SMP-ID</em> that <strong>must not be changed</strong> afterwards</li>
    <li>For the new style NAPTR lookup (from November 1<sup>st</sup>, 2025):
      <ul>
        <li>The SMP server exposes the mandatory read-only APIs on port 80 with http and/or on port 443 with https</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>At the end of the CNAME to NAPTR migration (from February 1<sup>st</sup>, 2026):
      <ul>
        <li>The SMP server exposes the mandatory read-only APIs exclusively on port 443 with https</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
  </ul>
</p>

<a name="create-smp"></a>
<h2>Create SMP at SML</h2>
<p>
  Every SMP must initially be registered to the SML. That needs to happen exactly once.
  Therefore you need to provide the following elements:
  <ul>
    <li>SMP X.509 certificate</li>
    <li>SMP-ID</li>
    <li>
      IP address of the machine (<em>physical address</em>).<br/>
      This may be defaulted to <code>1.1.1.1</code> as the public URL is the only mandatory part used by the SML.
    </li>  
    <li>Public URL of the SMP (<em>logical address</em>)</li>
  </ul>
</p>

<p>
  The following actions are taking place on the SML side:
  <ul>
    <li>The X.509 certificate is validated</li>
    <li>The uniqueness of the SMP-ID is verified</li>
    <li>The consistency of the provided parameters is checked</li>
    <li>A local database entry is created, that links the SMP-ID and parts of the X.509 certificate together</li>
  </ul>
</p>

<p>
  Note: this intermediate DNS record is helpful, if the public URL of an SMP changes. Instead of changing all participants that are
    linked to an SMP (which can be very many) only this single DNS record is changed, because all participant records are just
    CNAME records pointing to this "publisher" record.     
</p>

<p>
  Note: when using <em>phoss SMP</em> you have a GUI to do this smoothly at "Administration | SML | SML registration".
  Alternatively you can perform it via <a href="/public/menuitem-tools-smp-sml">the SMP-SML Tools</a> on this site.
</p>

<a name="update-smp"></a>
<h2>Update SMP at SML</h2>
<p>
  If the public URL or domain name of an SMP changes, this information must be propagated to the respective SML.
  The change of an SMP-ID is <strong>not</strong> foreseen, so this value must stay consistent.
  The change of an SMP certificate (e.g. because of expiration) can also <strong>not</strong> be done with
    this process. BDMSL foresees a specific process for this that is described at
    <a href="/public/menuitem-docs-peppol-cert-update">Peppol Certificate update</a>.
</p>

<p>
  The following elements are needed to update the SMP registration in the SML:
  <ul>
    <li>SMP X.509 certificate (must be the same as for initial registration)</li>
    <li>SMP-ID (must be the same as for initial registration)</li>
    <li>
      IP address of the machine (<em>physical address</em>).<br/>
      This may be defaulted to <code>1.1.1.1</code> as the public URL is the only mandatory part used by the SML.
    </li>
    <li>Public URL of the SMP (<em>logical address</em>)</li>
  </ul>
</p>

<p>
  The following actions are taking place on the SML side:
  <ul>
    <li>The X.509 certificate is validated</li>
    <li>The existence of the SMP-ID is verified</li>
    <li>It is checked whether the SMP-ID is linked to the provided X.509 certificate</li>
    <li>The consistency of the provided parameters is checked</li>
    <li>The local database entry, that links the SMP-ID and X.509 certificate together, is updated</li>
    <li>Each participant linked to the provided SMP-ID needs an update to it DNS record</li>
  </ul>
</p>

<p>
  Note: when using <em>phoss SMP</em> you have a GUI to do this smoothly at "Administration | SML | SML registration".
  Alternatively you can perform it via <a href="/public/menuitem-tools-smp-sml">the SMP-SML Tools</a> on this site.
</p>


<a name="delete-smp"></a>
<h2>Delete SMP from SML</h2>
<p>
  If an SMP leaves the network, after all participants were migrated to different SMPs, it must unregister itself
  from the SML.
</p>

<p>
  Note: don't test this functionality if you already have participants registered, since all participant DNS entries
  will also be deleted.
</p>

<p>
  The following elements are needed to delete the SMP registration from the SML:
  <ul>
    <li>SMP X.509 certificate (must be the same as for initial registration)</li>
    <li>SMP-ID (must be the same as for initial registration)</li>
  </ul>
</p>

<p>
  The following actions are taking place on the SML side:
  <ul>
    <li>The X.509 certificate is validated</li>
    <li>The existence of the SMP-ID is verified</li>
    <li>It is checked whether the SMP-ID is linked to the X.509 certificate</li>
    <li>The local database entries for all participants that are linked to that SMP-ID are deleted</li>
    <li>The local database entry for the provided SMP-ID is deleted</li>
    <li>All DNS records for participants linked to the SMP-ID are deleted</li>
  </ul>
</p>

<p>
  Note: when using <em>phoss SMP</em> you have a GUI to do this smoothly at "Administration | SML | SML registration".
  Alternatively you can perform it via <a href="/public/menuitem-tools-smp-sml">the SMP-SML Tools</a> on this site.
</p>

<a name="create-participant"></a>
<h2>Create participant in SMP and SML</h2>
<p>
  Before you can register new participants, ensure you registered your SMP to the SML as <a href="#create-smp">stated above</a>. 
</p>

<p>
  Each participant <strong>must</strong> be registered at the SML so that it can be addressed in the network.
  The following elements need to be provided to make it work:
  <ul>
    <li>SMP X.509 certificate</li>
    <li>SMP-ID</li>
    <li>Participant ID</li>
  </ul>
</p>


<p>
  The following actions are taking place on the SML side:
  <ul>
    <li>The X.509 certificate is validated</li>
    <li>The existence of the SMP-ID is verified</li>
    <li>It is checked whether the SMP-ID is linked to the X.509 certificate</li>
    <li>The consistency of the provided parameters is checked</li>
    <li>A local database entry is created, that links the SMP-ID and the participant identifier</li>
    <li>
      A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NAPTR_record" target="_blank">DNS NAPTR</a> record in the form of 
        <code>strip-trailing(base32(sha-256(lowercase(<em>ID-VALUE</em>))),"=")+"."+<em>ID-SCHEME</em>+"."+<em>DNSZONE</em></code>
        is created.<br />
      <em>ID-SCHEME</em> is part of the input parameter - the scheme part of the participant identifier (usually this is <code>iso6523-actorid-upis</code>)<br />
      <em>ID-VALUE</em> is also part of the input parameter - the value part of the participant identifier<br />
      <em>DNSZONE</em> is the DNS zone in which the SML operates -
        for the production SML that is <code>edelivery.tech.ec.europa.eu</code> and 
        for the test SMK this is <code>acc.edelivery.tech.ec.europa.eu</code>.<br />
      The DNS entry itself is a <em>NAPTR</em> record pointing to the SMP URL (!) 
        provided at the SMP to SML registration process (see above).<br />
    </li>
  </ul>
</p>

<p>
  Note: the changes to the DNS may not be directly visible to you, because the propagation
    of new entries can take up to 24 hours to be replicated to all distributed nodes.
</p>

<p>
  Note: when using <em>phoss SMP</em> this is done implicitly if you create a service group
    but only if SML connection is enabled.
</p>

<a name="delete-participant"></a>
<h2>Delete participant from SMP and SML</h2>
<p>
  If a participant is no longer needed, it must be manually unregistered from the SML.
</p>

<p>
  The following elements are needed to delete the SMP registration from the SML:
  <ul>
    <li>SMP X.509 certificate (must be the same as for initial registration)</li>
    <li>Participant ID</li>
  </ul>
</p>

<p>
  The following actions are taking place on the SML side:
  <ul>
    <li>The X.509 certificate is validated</li>
    <li>The existence of the Participant ID is verified</li>
    <li>It is checked whether the Participant ID is linked to the X.509 certificate</li>
    <li>The local database entry for the provided Participant ID is deleted</li>
    <li>The DNS NAPTR record for that Participant ID is deleted</li>
  </ul>
</p>

<p>
  Note: the changes to the DNS may not be directly visible to you, because the propagation
    of new entries can take up to 24 hours to be replicated to all distributed nodes.
</p>

<p>
  Note: of course the SML deletes both node types (CNAME and NAPTR) - it is just differentiated
    here for alignment with the Peppol migrations
</p>

<p>
  Note: when using <em>phoss SMP</em> this is done implicitly if you delete a service group
    but only if SML connection is enabled.
</p>

<!-- 
<a name="migrate-participant"></a>
<h2>Migrate participant from one SMP to another SMP</h2>
<p>
  TODO
</p>
 -->
<a name="references"></a>
<h2>References</h2>
<p>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="https://docs.peppol.eu/edelivery/">Peppol SML and SMP specifications</a></li>
  </ul>
</p>
